<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The clothiers complaint, or, Reasons for passing the bill against the Blackwell-Hall factors, &amp;c. shewing it to be a publick good / humbly offered to the Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23714</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07880723</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07880723</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33482)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1202:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The clothiers complaint, or, Reasons for passing the bill against the Blackwell-Hall factors, &amp;c. shewing it to be a publick good / humbly offered to the Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Textile industry --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40262:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40262:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Clothiers Complaint: OR REASONS FOR Paſſing the BILL, Againſt the <hi>Blackwell-Hall</hi> Factors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing it to be a PUBLICK GOOD: Humbly Offer'd to the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <q>Ad ſanitatem gradus eſt, noviſſe morbum, <bibl>
                  <hi>Eraſ.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers</hi>-Hall, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40262:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40262:2"/>
            <p>TO endeavour to ſhew how great an influence the Woollen Manufacture hath upon the value of Lands and good payment of Rents in the Country, would be a needleſs undertaking to ſo prudent a Counſel, and but lighting a Candle to the Sun.</p>
            <p>And ſince the unanſwerable Experience of twenty years laſt paſt, hath manifeſt an alteration in thoſe affairs, and that there is an apparent fall in the rates of Lands in the general; and ſince it is as evident that the Woollen-Manufacture is the principal branch of our Trade, and only Staple Commodity of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, which gives life and motion to all other Trades. It can be no needleſs enquiry to examine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any unneceſſary Letts ſprung up in ſo long a Tract of Time, which may-either check or retard the free courſe of this Maſter-wheel of our Trade, ſerving a private Intereſt at the expence of the Publick.</p>
            <p>Or whether the Profit ariſing out of the Woollen-Manufacture be equally divided between the Country and the City, as it juſtly belongs.</p>
            <p>I ſhall wholly confine my ſelf (in this Addreſs) to my own Province in plain matters of fact, and make it my task to ſhew, that there is a defect in both theſe particulars, which now offers to be redreſt in our Bill. Wherein, altho' my capacity will not reach to the heighth of the matter, yet it may give ſome light, and make way for better Judgment: And herein (being invaded in point of right) I hope I may depend upon the moſt favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conſtruction, being an act of neceſſity, and not of choice.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance and intent of our Bill being only this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> Blackwell-Hall, <hi>the common Market of</hi> England <hi>for Cloth, ſhall be wholly at the liberty of Clothiers, to ſell their Cloth to Merchants and Woollen Drapers, according to ancient Cuſtom. And the Factors of</hi> Blackwell-Hall, <hi>who hath now got the poſſeſſion of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40262:3"/>ſaid Hall, ſhall be diſpoſſeſt, and a freedom to Clothiers to ſend up Servants out of the Country (under reſtrictions from buying of Wool, and ſettled Sallaries) for the accommodation of the Market, where is appears needful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That all Cloth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is brought to</hi> London, <hi>ſhall be</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>ſold in this publick Market of</hi> Blackwell-Hall, <hi>in the proper time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready appointed for that purpoſe; and as it is now under Obligation to be there enter'd, and to pay a certain Duty to the Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That all Cloth made of Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ous and Noyles, or of any worſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity than Fleece-Wool, ſhall be made with a diſtinction, that the Buyer may not be deceived.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That all long Cloths, of what County ſoever, ſhall be made of one limited length; which is the full import of our Bill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſign of this Bill being ſolely a publick Good, and that which concerns the general Intereſt of the Nation, I hope will be impartially conſidered by every generous <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Man, and true Patriot of his Country, whoſe protection it juſtly claims, ſo far as it hath that appearance.</p>
            <p>It doth indeed immediately concern the Clothiers, by whom, were the matter left to be decided by a majority, it would be but a ſhort conteſt: And we uſually ſay, that he that wears the Shooe knows beſt where it pincheth: As general, I think in the ſence of the Calamity, as the conſult of Mice in the Fable, but too much of the timorouſneſs of thoſe little Animals, ready to ſhrink back, at the difficulty of putting on the Bell, being ſo far brought under Dominion.</p>
            <p>And altho' the Clothiers are a conſiderable number of Men in the Nation, yet belonging to different Counties, and for the moſt part engaged in ſuch buſineſs that requires conſtant atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, they cannot ſo well wait upon publick affairs of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as thoſe that are always together upon the place, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and have plenty of Money to forward any publick Affairs, the command, as well of their Maſters Purſes as their own. But if this Bill hath the impreſs of a publick Good upon it, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf it will not be obſtructed with Shadows.</p>
            <p>A long diſcourſe from a bauling Factor, in diſguiſe of a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, in commendation of Pinion-Cloth, when he himſelf is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40262:3"/>ſinking in the ſame bottom, may be of as little ſignification to the Publick, as from a condemn'd Perſon at <hi>Tyburn;</hi> it being ſo well known to be a deceitful ſort of Cloth, but poſſibly a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubject than the juſtification of his own practice: Both which may chance to paſs for good reaſon under the tender affection of a Daughter.</p>
            <p>Nor can the <hi>York ſhire</hi> Intereſt, whoſe Pinion Cloth hath of late Years ſheltered it ſelf in imitation of <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> and other Fleece-Wool-Cloth, and unwilling to appear in its own guiſe, be of any real ſignification in this affair, whatſoever inſtuence they may have upon their Members.</p>
            <p>And the leaſt colour of oppoſition from the Merchant may be confirmation enough to the Country-Gentleman, that the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comes from the ſpring of his own Intereſt, who be ſure would not oppoſe the Bill, if Cloth thereby was not like to be the dearer to him.</p>
            <p>And I hope the Land-Taxes in the Country at this time may as juſtly claim a conſideration, as the ſupport of the ſplendor and gallantry of a Factors Coach in the City. — But to proceed to the merit of our Bill.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place, we are diſpoſſeſſed of our right in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Market of <hi>Blackwell-Hall.</hi> The ſpacious buildings of <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel-Hall,</hi> equally accommodated to Trade, were altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for the benefit of Clothiers, to ſell their Cloth to Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Woollen-Drapers; and until about thirty years laſt paſt, ſo practiſed.</p>
            <p>By act of Common-Council of the City, moſt Cloth that is brought to <hi>London,</hi> muſt be enter'd at <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> and pay a Duty, which muſt be grounded upon reaſon; and that the Clothier ſhall have an accommodation for his Money: The ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Rule of Buying and Selling in this publick Market, is, that no Freeman of the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall have liberty to ſell any Goods there; and that none but Freemen ſhall have liberty to buy any Cloth.</p>
            <p>This courſe of Trade is now wholly diverted in the Selling part, and all the Windows of <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> that are convenient to ſhew Cloth, are taken up by Factors, many of which are Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the Clothier excluded from the Sale of his own Goods, and diſpoſſeſt of his ancient right.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40262:4"/>2. In the next place, of the Factors themſelves, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>Blackwell-Hall</hi> is well in memory, of about thirty Years ſtanding; they gained their beſt footing in the ſickneſs time and fire of <hi>London.</hi> Miſchiefs ſeldom come alone. In number about thirty, and very few of this number that hath any juſt right to the practice they now follow, having ſerved Apprenticeſhips to other Trades. For your accomodation (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' the number is not great) you may make choice of a Factor ſprung from almoſt any profeſſion, an Oyl man, a Cloth drawer, a Tobacconiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The regular Factors, their Apprentices, moſt of them make a ſhort flouriſh, and then break. I think there may be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor found in the ſame place, who hath had three or four A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices ſucceſſively broke. The pleaſantneſs of their living, exceeds any Trade that I know of; only one morning in a week that requires their exact attendance: Great leaſure the remaining part to ſettle the publick affairs of the Nation, (having ſeveral Apprentices to perform the laborious parts) in which (being become the chief Maſter of the Woollen-Manufacture and ſuch opportunities by inſinuating Letters of Commerce) they have had no ſmall ſtroke.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quin laniunt mundum tanta eſt diſcordia fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum, Everſus</hi> F <hi>by the Intereſt of S</hi> Chipnam.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The diſpoſal of a piece of Cloth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining twenty two yards, and in value Six or Seven Pounds; the Factoridge is four Shillings: All other charge of Poſt-Letters, Hallidge, Porteridge, Preſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be paid by the Clothier; which is now brought up very near to the value of the Factoridge. In an accompt of the ſale of two pieces of Cloth, where the Factoridge was eight Shillings; the extraordinary charge brought it up to ſixteen Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſix Pence.</p>
            <p>In another accompt of the ſale of nine pieces of Cloth, the extraordinary charge reckoned by the Factor, was twelve Pence a piece more than his Factoridge; and the Cloth ſold twelve Pence a Yard under the Clothier's price he left them at; both matters of Fact, and to be proved.</p>
            <p>The new preſſing of Cloth is become an intolerable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then upon the Clothier; and the returning of Cloth after bought, grown ſo familiar of late Years, that there is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in a ſale many times in three Weeks or a Month; which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40262:4"/>practice hath been brought on by the Factor, with many more that at this time will be too tedious to mention.</p>
            <p>The next part of the Factor's profit is out of the Wooll that makes the Cloth, which is uſually three Pence a Pound out of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wooll, and five Shillings a Pack out of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll; the beſt part of his gains.</p>
            <p>All the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wooll that is brought into <hi>London,</hi> is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought up by the Factors: What comes into <hi>Exeter,</hi> they many times get into their Hands, and hath bought a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable quantity at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and ſold it at three Pence a Pound profit to their Clothiers, who have lived but ten or fifteen Miles diſtant from that place: Matter of Fact, and the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this profit is admirable.</p>
            <p>If they make a bad Debt for the Clothier, it is no rule for the loſs of their Factoridge, a ſtated caſe, and always Effects in their hands to make good for the Wool; and I am ſatisfied the greateſt part of it is paid for with the Clothiers own Money, having many times conſiderable credit from the Merchant. The diſpoſal of it afterwards is no leſs remarkable, where one Bag in five is not ſeen by the Clothier before ſent down, and the Price enter'd to his account when ſent; ſo that the whole of one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Profit hath been computed at 3000 <hi>l. per annum.</hi> How far this extraordinary Charge, upon the commanding Commodity of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, is conſiſtent with a Publick Good, I leave to better Judgments.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But farther, they are become Clothiers as well as Factors; as Brewers become Maulſters, and have their Agents in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries to make Cloth for them; this chiefly incouraged in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Intereſt of the Wool-brogger: And here I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give a full account of this Affair, without taking notice of the Packer, who is come in for a ſhare; and indeed an excellent contrived Platform!</p>
            <p>The ſale of Cloth in <hi>London</hi> is wholly in the hands of Factors and Packers, and the Merchants being poſſeſs'd, that they have a greater benefit thereby, than if they bought it of the Clothiers. It hath been uſual for a conſiderable Merchant to leave the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of four or five hundred Cloths to a conſiderable Packer, and take his account made up to his hand; the Packer, being under ſeveral Obligations to the Merchant, in point of his own Trade, will be ſure to be more of his ſide than the Clothiers, yet not ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40262:5"/>ſteady, but that an immediate Intereſt may a little byaſs; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the ſuddain and prodigious flights that happen in our days.</p>
            <p>The Wool broggers being become the greateſt buyers of Wool in <hi>England,</hi> all <hi>Middleſex, Eſſex, Kant,</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> being wholly in their hands, and a great ſhare of other Counties, tho' nearer to Clothing Pares than to <hi>London,</hi> the beſt way afterwards to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Wool, is to ſuch Clodiers that they can command; but there being no conveniency without its inconveniency, too great a hazard in ſuch a Trade, and a farther conveniency in helping of a ſorry Commodity, they come to this agreement with the Factor or Packer, that if either of theſe can help them to a Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier that will take off their Wool, and afterwards ſell the Cloth for him, and ſecure him their Money for the Wool, that they ſhall have ſuch a conſtant Salary, out of every pack of Wool, ſent him down; which is eaſie enough agreed upon, over a Glaſs of Wine, being all at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Packer can eaſily forward the Sale of any Man's Cloth, and will not be wanting, being continually minded by a certain Intereſt.</p>
            <p>The Factor hath ſo much out of the Wool, and ſo much Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoridge out of every Cloth, and he will take care to furniſh with Oyl, and a little Money Weekly to pay the Work-People, and the utmoſt of his endeavors will not be wanting to keep this Wheel going, and no better ſhelter for ſmall faults, than a certain Intereſt: This practice hath ſo far prevail'd, that above a quarter of Merchants Cloth is made in this Channel, I know not whether miſtaken, if I had ſaid half. This unhappy miſchief ſolely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd by the ſeparation of the Merchant and Clothier. And want of Judgment in Cloth, in the Merchant, which likewiſe ſprings from the ſame cauſe; whilſt Merchants bought their Cloth at <hi>Blackwel-Hall,</hi> and examined it at their own Houſes, which was the practice of former time: this maintain'd Experience and Judgment in Cloth, which is not to be procur'd and maintain'd but by ſuch a frequent uſe; and for incouragement herein, our Cloth is a cleanly Commodity, and pleaſant to be felt; but, quoth the Proverb, <hi>A Man's own buſineſs never dirts his Fingers:</hi> And the Apprentice which had always a hand in pooling the Cloth over the Perch, was hereby bred up to knowledge in the Cloth Trade, and when he kept the Caſh at home, and paid the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40262:5"/>Clothier, his hand was full of buſineſs, and much under the Maſter's Eye; and how many young Mens ruine hath been ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this alteration of Trade? who, inſtead thereof, get a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Idleneſs. I ſhall not ſpecifie, but upon ſerious reflection it will appear to be a melancholy Thought. And the Cloth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now wholly managed at Packers Houſes, and they ſenſible enough of their own Intereſt, the next ſet of Merchants will think, that Judgment in Cloth is no part of the Merchants Trade.</p>
            <p>It can be no great credit to be confin'd to Spectacles in the prime time of a Man's Age; eſpecially ſuch a ſort that are liable to be dazled by the leaſt white Miſt, which will make a Cloth made of thin hungry <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Wool, look with ſuch a thick bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; that it ſhall exceed a Cloth made of <hi>Somerſet-ſhire, Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> or <hi>Hamp ſhire</hi> Wool, which is much of a ſuperiour quality. I thought ſome time ſince, that it would be an advantage in the Sale of Cloth, to write upon it, that it was made of <hi>London</hi> Wool, finding that ſort ſo much prefer'd: And I think, <hi>Crede quod habes &amp; habes,</hi> hath made a greater progreſs in the Woollen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture than in Religion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And this leads me to ſhew how this practice hath prevail'd to the imbaſing of our Cloth. Good Wine, we ſay, needs no Buſh; and before theſe Factors Days and Trade came into this Channel, it was a uſual Saying, that the Clothier needed not a Merchant, if his Cloth was good; and the chiefeſt care was to maintain a credit in Trade: A Cloth-mark reckon'd of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable value, which was the undoubted Intereſt of the Nation.</p>
            <p>The Clothier that made the Cloth, ſold it to the <hi>Merchant,</hi> and heard the faults of his own Cloth; and forc'd ſometimes, not only to promiſe amendment himſelf, but to go home and tell <hi>Joan,</hi> to have the Wool better pick'd, and the Yarn better Spun.</p>
            <p>The Wool was uſually bought in the Summer, and a good Stock of Goods ſeen in the Clothiers hand, which is a great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the making of good Cloth; and Wool held up, in thoſe days to a Price that the former had incouragement.</p>
            <p>This great Wheel of Trade, that is now kept going, muſt go ſwiftly round againſt a Shipping, the Cloths like the Sons of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> of a nimble Birth; the Wool ſent from <hi>London</hi> this Week, and returned in Cloth in five or ſix Weeks, which is the delight of a Factor, and proportionably as ſlow, as ſoon as buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40262:6"/>is over; the alotment of Wool to a Cloth, in the firſt place, by the Agent in the Country, is very ſcanting: To which being added, the condition of it from a moiſt Cellar, and bad ways carrying down, great part coming down in the Winter, muſt needs afford but a lean Commodity; laid in the Loom nine quarters and an half wide, which formerly was laid twelve quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and as much Cloth dreſt by two Men, as could be done by four, was the Cloth well made, and had its deſerts: No care in the Country, but a quick diſpatch to <hi>London</hi> to the Factors, and how to make an addition to the ſmall Salary, by putting off all ſorts of Commodities to the Work-People, which is come almoſt to a general practice in this way of Trade, poſſibly five ſhillings in Money, and fifteen in Commodities.</p>
            <p>☞ This brings to Market ten Cloths, with the ſame Wool that formerly made but nine, which always keeps a ſtock at Market, and therein anſwers the Merchants end in beating down the Price: And as it affects the Publick in the loſs of our Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abroad, it likewiſe immediately concerns us at home in the Price of Wool. In fifty thouſand Cloths that are likely to be ſent to <hi>Turky,</hi> which contain in the Water thirty ſix yards each Cloth, and ſtrain'd to forty four, and as great a proportion in breadth (a great diſparagement to our Reputation and miſchief to the Publick;) there wants ſix or eight pounds of Wool one Cloth with the other, to make the ſame yards of Cloth to the goodneſs they were of in former times, when the Clothiers ſold their own Cloth: This quantity of Wool remaining upon the Farmer's hand, which ſhould have been in the ſame yards of Cloth, muſt needs make an odds in the Price of Wool; and had that quantity of Wool been added to the ſame yards of Cloth, the Cloth had been double the value of the ſaid Wool better, in the true merit and ſervice of it; And whatſoever may be ſaid of new Drapery, and humouring of Markets abroad, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than in Breadths to anſwer the Habits of all Countries, I take to be nothing but private Intereſt. And that Statute of the Fourth of <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, Chapter the Second, holding Cloth to a weight, was very agreeable with the true Intereſt of the Nation: the weight of Cloth being duly proportioned to its length and goodneſs, according to good advice, eſpecially in low Price Merchants Cloth; and ought again to be conſidered how valuable the Reputation of any Commodity is, to its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40262:6"/>abroad, is plainly ſeen by the ſingle inſtance of the <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Bays, which carry the Trade in all Parts abroad, by their due care in preſerving the merit and goodneſs of them; and indeed Reputation can come from no other ground.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But the moſt material Miſchief that the Country ſuffers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, wholly introduc'd by the Factor, is the long credit given with Cloth.</p>
            <p>The ſtandard Rule with moſt Cloth that is Sold, is ſix Months; which, if paid in nine, is not thought bad payment, many times not in twelve, ſometimes fifteen.</p>
            <p>To ſupport this extorted and prepoſtrous Credit, and drive Trade round too, the whole Country is forc'd to raiſe its <hi>poſſe Comitatus,</hi> and like a ſtring of Horſes in a Team, many times forc'd to lend their aſſiſtances at a dead lift. The Clothier's Stock, and the utmoſt of his Credit firſt goes, then the Card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, the Weaver, ſtrain their Credit to the utmoſt: Afterwards the Butcher and the Chandler lend as far as they think ſafe: And the Farmer ſtrains his Landlords patience as far as ever he can; and if <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Rent be cleared at <hi>Lady day,</hi> he is a very good Tenant.</p>
            <p>In former days, a Clotheir was reckon'd to be able to keep one broad Loom well imploy'd, with fifty pounds, if he bought his Yarn; or if he made his Cloth out of the Wool, with one hundred pounds, which now is not to be done with three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds in this way of Trade; and the Clothier turn'd his Stock three times in thoſe days for once now: He Sold his Cloth to the <hi>Merchant,</hi> and receiv'd his Money, and went out of Town again in two or three days; it was then thought a reflection upon the <hi>Merchant</hi> that he dealt with, if he tarried longer, ſuppoſing he waited for his Money. <hi>Hou quantum mutatus ab illo!</hi> Now three Weeks waiting upon a Factor or Packer for a little Money, all ſwallowed up in the great City, and the Country ſtarved; and this chiefly introduc'd by the deſign of the Factor, to keep the Clothier from buying Wool of the <hi>Merchant,</hi> or where he hath no advantage by it.</p>
            <p>This Credit doth not ſpring from a real want of Money to buy Cloth; there be many <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Woollen-Drapers</hi> that now buy Cloth and make good payment, that would buy twice as much, and do the like, if the Trade was more in their hands,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40262:7"/>which would be the conſequence, if the Clothiers ſold their own Cloth; and hereby there would be a greater Stock of Money drawn into the Cloth Trade, than would be withdrawn by the Factors and Wool-broggers; and whatſoever Clothier was inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious at his Trade, he would find more favour hence, if his Stock was ſmall, than he hath now from a Factor.</p>
            <p>The Factors by this deſigned Credit, hath carried the Cloth Trade into too wide a diſtance (I wiſh it be brought ſafe home:) Few old Clothiers knew any ſuch place as <hi>Wapping,</hi> where a pair of Shoes may now be worn out a dunning for the Money of two or three Pieces of Cloth: And indeed, a great ſhame that the beſt Commodity of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation ſhould be thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever Commodity is bought by the <hi>Merchant</hi> beſides Cloth, as Tin and Lead, they meet with good payment, and the Cloth found the eaſieſt place to lean upon: And no part of the Wollen-Manufacture, that is ſold according to the Will of the Maker, but meets with good payment, <hi>Colcheſter-Bays, Stuffs, Serges, Perpetuana</hi>'s, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But here is another Snake in the Graſs, lurking in this Credit, which is very prejudicial to the Country, and poſſibly little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; the <hi>Clothier</hi>'s Stock being got into the <hi>Merchant</hi>'s hand, and no Money to be raiſed out of any Goods he hath upon hand at Shear-time: The <hi>Merchants</hi> hereby govern the <hi>Clothiers</hi> at that time as they pleaſe, and thereby govern the Price of Wool. We always find it the difficults time to get Money out of the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> hand at Shear-time. If the <hi>Clothier</hi> had his Money in his own hand, he hath ſeveral reaſons to lay it out at that time, and this of greater moment than obſervation, whatſoever pretence for Credit may be made on the <hi>Merchants</hi> ſide, by their long Voyages to <hi>Turky,</hi> the contrary for many years paſt hath appear'd, in their deferring their Shippings, for their advantage in Buying and Selling; nimble Shippings would make nimble returns, and very much for the good of the Publick; and the inconveniencies they found by giving Credit with their Goods in <hi>Turky,</hi> hath made poſitive order againſt it. And the hazard the <hi>Clothier</hi> run with his Eſtate, in the preſent management of Trade, is not the leaſt of his misfortunes; in great part of the Cloth that is ſold, he is in two hazards, beſides the Principle, the Factor and Packer, whoſe Receipt to the <hi>Merchant</hi> is a full diſcharge.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40262:7"/>7. And this leads me, humbly to offer a ſhort account of our Calamities from our broken Factors, omitting the bad Debts that they have been the Authors of, which are unaccountable. And here could I firſt ſummon the <hi>Clothiers</hi> of <hi>Sheppen-mallet,</hi> to give an exact account of their Factor <hi>Stroud,</hi> and the unexpected diſappointment of their ſupport of old Age, after a laborious Trade: Or the Creditors of <hi>Duncome,</hi> to ſet out the variety of his footſteps, it would be a melancholy Hiſtory: Or did I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon freſher Inſtances, I ſhould find as many Creditors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to one broken Factor, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> received ſtripes from the <hi>Jews:</hi> I can't but wiſh their Guilt in the place of his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and each Creditor the content of one ſtripe, according to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law; and farther add, that had the firſt broken Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor been deſervedly Whipt, we had never had one Factor broke three times, which practice is grown ſo familiar, theſe late years, and ſo afflicting to careful Traders, I think it deſerves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration in the general, and a Law wanting in ſuch caſes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where there can be no fair accompt given of misfortunes; it being impoſſible for a Factor to break, or meet with any loſs, and no more excuſe than ſpending forty ſhillings a Week, when his Wages was but twenty. The time would fail me to keep to particulars herein, and our Loſſes beyond my Arithmitick: or ſhould I endeavour to ſet forth the variety of Abuſes that hath been practiced in this way of Trade, their placing bad Debts to Accompt as they ſee fit, pretending Credit ſometimes when rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Money received, and the like, it would be too large a task to enter upon, and, which adds to the Calamity, the miſchief is like to encreaſe with their number, which is like to double every ſeven years; ſome of them having two or three Apprentices. I have given an account of the current profit of our Factors, and now of another ſort, that we parted with to our loſs; we are likewiſe liable to a third ſort, which I think are <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> Factors; theſe will be ſure to Cheat as oft as they have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. Should a Clothier die and leave an Eſtate in one of theſe Factors hands, and make a diſpoſal according to his own Judgment, of his Eſtate, he will be very likely to make a <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Will; in which particular, we are not without a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inſtance: And thus much of our Factors.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond part of my promiſe; as likewiſe to the ſecond part of our Bill, to ſhew that there is an unequal di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40262:8"/>of the Profit ariſing out of the Woollen Manufacture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Country and the City.</p>
            <p>The growth and perfection of the Woollen-Manufacture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intirely owing to the Country, and the Shepherds care, the chief ſpring of our Riches and Treaſure. The King, as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, being Fed by the Field, and the Riches of Foreign Parts not to be procur'd and brought home, but by a Value ſent hence, which is wholly comprehended in the Fleece; a fair ſhare of the Profit ariſing out of the Woollen-Manufacture, cannot be denied to the Country. And there can be no equal diviſion of this Profit between the Country and the City, but by a fair Sale of the Woollen-Manufacture in a publick Market, where each In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt may fairly ſtruggle, as in all Buying and Selling, and be upon equal ground to the leaſt tittle, which is the niceſt part of Trade; diſcretion and prudence in timing of Affairs in a Market or Fair, doth many times give the Buyer an advantage, when his occaſion is as urgent for the Commodity, as the Seller for his Money; and Experience ſhews us, that when there happens the leaſt diſproportion on each ſide, the Commodity either ſinks or riſeth. In all Trades the Seller, where the Intereſt is his own) conſults his Reaſon to make the moſt of his Commodity, and for his Government, diligently obſerveth what demand there is for his Goods: The Buyer on the other hand, uſeth his Induſtry to get as good a penniworth as he can, and obſerveth the Plenty of the Commodity and number of Chapmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and between theſe honeſt and equal conteſts, a full ſatisfaction on both ſides doth fairly center; in a little ebbing and flowing, if a little ground loſt before a Shipping, recovered again when the Shipping comes; And for the juſt preſervation hereof, the care of our Anceſtors hath not appear'd in any thing more, than that publick Markets for Buying and Selling ſhould be duly preſerved, that there ſhould be no Fore-ſtalling Commotlities coming to Market, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the ſtrict care of the City of <hi>London,</hi> that all Cloth ſhall be brought to this publick Market of <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> ſeems to come from the ſame conſideration.</p>
            <p>The Woollen-Manufacture now being ſo conſiderable a part of our livelihood in the Country, and the value of Wool hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great an effect upon the value of Land, and the Market of <hi>Blackwel-Hall,</hi> the moſt conſiderable Market of <hi>England</hi> for our Cloth, there ought to be a fair adjuſtment of the Rules of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40262:8"/>this common Market, between the Country and City, with all imaginable caution, and as ſtrict an injunction to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, that the Seller may be upon equal ground with the Buyer.</p>
            <p>And the ancient Rules of this Market of <hi>Blackwel-Hall,</hi> ſettled in former time, ſeems to be a fair accommodation between Country and City.</p>
            <p>Many of the Clothiers having a conſiderable Journey of an hundred miles to this Market, it ſeems to me to be conſidered in the timing of the Market, allowing the firſt part of the Week for the Journey. This Market to begin upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> morning eight of the Clock, to continue until eleven of the Clock, and then ſhut up, to begin in the Afternoon at two of the Clock, and continue until four, and then ſhut up: In like manner, all day upon <hi>Friday,</hi> and <hi>Saturday</hi> morning until eleven of the Clock, then to be lock'd up, and no more open'd upon any occaſion of Trade, until the next Week Market: and no Cloth any where elſe in Town to be bought at the firſt hand, but at <hi>Blackwell-Hall;</hi> which I think to be very well proportion'd in time between Buyer and Seller: This kept the <hi>Merchant</hi> to ſome diſpatch with the <hi>Clothier,</hi> and he fairly ſaw what demand there was for Cloth.</p>
            <p>The duty paid at the Hall for the Entry of every Cloth, was, I think, one Penny a Cloth; and what Cloth was not ſold by the Clothier (if he had no mind to wait another Market, which was very unuſual in thoſe days) was plac'd up in the Store-Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which are provided for that purpoſe, until the Clothier came up again, or he order'd ſome other Clothier to act in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him; and I think, free of all Charge, or at leaſt ought to be; the fatiegue of ſo tedious a Journey, and the conſiderable advantage the City of <hi>London</hi> make in other particulars, may fairly deſerve the free accommodation of a Market; and the practice of all Cities and Towns in <hi>England</hi> confirm the ſame. A well made piece of Cloth, brought to its perfection, contains more merit and beauty than to be expos'd to the leaſt inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency: and not the leaſt allowance to be made in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which, I hope, will be fairly adjuſted.</p>
            <p>I will now give a true and impartial Account, of the preſent management of the ſale of Cloth, and the practice of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40262:9"/>Market of <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> to the beſt of my knowledge.</p>
            <p>All Cloth, according to ancient Cuſtom, is here Enter'd, and pay a Duty, I think, one Penny a Cloth, tho' many times carried directly to Packers Houſes, and what Cloth is continued in the Hall, pay one half penny a Week for each Piece of Cloth, which is now very conſiderable, by reaſon of ſo many Factors, who are willing to grace their Standings with as fair a ſhew of choice as they can, but all of them reckon'd to the Clothier, in the upper Hall, where it is moſt conſiderable: The Store Houſes of the ſaid Hall are let out to Factors for their accommodation, at a yearly Rent, ſome to other purpoſes, to hold Linnen, Yarn, or the like: What Money ariſeth out of this publick Market, by theſe ways and means, more than will defray the charge of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary attendance, is monthly paid into <hi>Chriſt Church</hi> Hoſpital, being very conſiderable, and diſpos'd of as the City Charity; from which Charity, and the conſiderable difficulty that ariſes from the due adjuſtment of the limits of ſo many ſtandings of the Factors, and ſupplying the vacancies that happen, with all the juſtice that may be, amongſt ſo many Pretenders: There are ſeveral Governours appointed by the City, to hear and determine all Occurrences of that nature that happen; and which is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle remarkable, there are ſome Factors got up into this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether in Compliment to the Clothiers, or whether from the ſcarcity of ſuch grave qualified Perſons, for ſo weighty a purpoſe, I know not; however, I think too great Favorites of the City to be ſtrenuous Contenders for the true Intereſt of the Country, in keeping up the Price of Cloth, and from hence, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle appearance of Succeſs at this Court, from any application that might be made by the Clothiers againſt the Factors.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all theſe creditable and good effects of ſo conſiderable and publick a Market, <hi>Blackwell-Hall</hi> is no more in effect than a Store-Houſe, and a place that the command of the City obligeth Cloth to be enter'd at; and the continuance of the Market from <hi>Thurſday</hi> to <hi>Saturday</hi> of no more ſignification than the preſerving an ancient Cuſtom: Here are a conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Woollen-Drapers upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> morning, to ſee what freſh Cloth is come up, or whether any thing new, but under no neceſſity of the Market, having been courted the day before with all the freſh Patterns of the Cloth, coming up by the Factors, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive practice to Trade in the general: And upon any day of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40262:9"/>the Week, can go to any Factors Hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e or Store Houſe, and buy what Cloth they pleaſe; nor indeed is the Sale of Cloth to theſe Woollen-Drapers in this publick Market of any real ſignification, for they conſtantly return half the Cloth that is there bought without giving a reaſon. This practice incouraged by a little pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Profit (I doubt) that hereby accrues to the Factor, by going ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ips in the new preſſing, a very unequal practice to the Maker; hereby if their judgment do a little err in the Market, it's certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rectifi'd by compare at home, and a conſult of Aſſiſtants: And a nice diſtinction in the true value of Cloth or Wool, is not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd without diligent obſervation, and the Clothier muſt be at a loſs, if his judgment in the leaſt fail him in the publick Market, in his Wool, whilſt he hath not the fair play of a publick Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket to balance it, and the return of Cloth by the Woollen-Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, after lain in his Shop a Fortnight or three Weeks, which is now very uſual, is very prejudicial to the Clothier in point of fancy in Colour; the Woollen-Draper hereby informs himſelf by his Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers that come in, whether the Colour will pleaſe or not, and there being a neceſſity of variety to humour the preſent genius of the World, this fancy ought to be decided by ſingle judgment in a publick Market; eſpecially ſince it's evident, that our Woollen-Cloth, by this fancy and variety is become more uſeful; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhews us, that a well-made Piece of true Scarlet, ſtrip'd with a good fancy in Black, may give a challenge to the whole World in the lining of a Chariot, not only for its true uſefulneſs and ſervice, but equal luſtre and beauty: And if fancy was ever regulated by the true Intereſt of the Nation, it may gain a greater advantage in Beds: No humour ſo gay, but here may be varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to anſwer it; which inconveniency to the Clothiers (had I not already balanced with the Factors) I might fairly place to their accompts. And for the <hi>Merchants</hi> Trade for <hi>Turky,</hi> there is no ſhadow of that at <hi>Blackwell Hall;</hi> or if any <hi>Merchant</hi> incline to buy Cloth at his own Houſe, ſo many ſamples are preſently ſent in by Factors, that Plenty makes him Poor, and he knows not which to gratifie. A Clothier may now ſtand by his Cloth in the beſt place he can find at <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> one Market after another, like an Owl in the Deſart, and never ſee a <hi>Merchant,</hi> which will ſoon enough attract a Kite or an Hawk, a Packer or a Factor, both which are Birds of Prey, in buying of Cloth to ſell it again, and the Clothier wholly becomes an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40262:10"/>Perſon in the Sale of his own Goods; as if he came from ſome remote part of the World, and could not ſpeak <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and knew not how to diſpoſe his own time, were it not for ſome ſociable Tabaconiſt-Shops, whom Cuſtom, and a little Profit, hath made a familiar entertainment; his Spirits kept up by the hopes of his Factor, who once a day will come to him, and ſhake him by the hand, and acquaint him, he is in hopes of a good Chapman, at a little abatement, and incourage a Compliance; but after all, the <hi>Merchant</hi> is gone out of Town for ten days, but doubt not of the full Price when he comes to Town, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Money advanc'd upon the old account, and <hi>Exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Clothier muſt be at a loſs for a <hi>Merchant,</hi> if the publick Market will not afford him one, and muſt be beholding to ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour aſſiſtance. The <hi>Merchant</hi> would come to the publick Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, if he was not ſatisfied that this practice of buying of Cloth was more for his profit. And if the Packer and Factor, who have the Sale of the Cloth, be more of the <hi>Merchants</hi> ſide than the Clothiers, how far may this prevail, by degrees, to the beating down of the Price of Cloth? The Packer's Houſe, in which there is a greater Trade for <hi>Merchants</hi> Cloth, than the publick Market of <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> is only free to ſuch <hi>Merchants</hi> as are his friends; ſuppoſing ſome great Packer, of Intereſt and Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſhould get into his hands moſt of the choiceſt Cloth of a Country, which may be eaſily done, if ſome conſiderable <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> will ſtick by him, and they agree together, that this Cloth ſhall wholly come into their hands; may not this be ſome kind of Monopoly; and ſome <hi>Merchants</hi> out-do others? I am ſure hereby a few great Packers grow vaſtly rich and impoveriſh others. Experience ſhews us, that as Trade is now managed, the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant</hi> never makes any advance in a dull time of Trade. The Packers many times prevail with their Clothiers to die Cloth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their account in the Summer, when there hath been a little proſpect of Trade in the Winter; at which time drying is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous, in which, if a miſcarriage, it lights upon the Clothier, and the longer time, at laſt, for payment, to be procured by the <hi>Merchant;</hi> and no Citizen but underſtands the value of Money, Seven <hi>per Cent.</hi> to the Exchequer, or otherwiſe. That which fool'd <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in Tranſubſtantiation, and he could never get over, is, at this time made good by ſome great Packers and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors: They have the ſame Clothiers at work for them in two
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40262:10"/>places at the ſame time; they work for them in the Country, with their hands, and in their Cloſets, by their Tallies, which is a Subſtance that equally effects the ſame end. This great City (were it not for the ſupport of life,) I think, would like <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> devour the Country
<note n="*" place="margin">Homo homini lupus.</note>. This being the preſent management of the Sale of our Woollen-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture, in undeniable matters of Fact, I ſhall not further inſiſt upon the unequal diviſion of the Profit between the Country and the City. A blot in Game is no blot until hit; and if the younger Brother hath out-witted the elder—</p>
            <p>I come now, in all ſubmiſſion, to the third part of our Bill, the marking of Pinion-Cloth.</p>
            <p>That Cloth made of Pinions and Noyles, is of a worſe quality than Cloth made of perfect Fleece-Wool, admits no diſpute, the one being made of the <hi>Holding</hi>-Staple of the Wool, the other with the Flocky part of the Wool, that is ſeparate from the long Staple. The quantity of Pinions that uſually ariſe out of this long Wool, is about two pound in twelve, in an ordinary way of making them.</p>
            <p>In the next place, when this Pinion-Cloth is made up, and Hot-preſs'd, the warieſt Buyer is liable to be deceived.</p>
            <p>The reſolution of former Parliaments, in this particular, may be of ſome moment to confirm the reaſonableneſs of it now, as in ſeveral Statutes appears, it was not admitted into Broad-Cloth; and the narrow Cloth to have one black Liſt, and the other a plain Selvage, as appears by the Statute of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quarto</hi> Jacobi <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note>. The quantity of theſe Pini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is much increas'd, as the Trade of Stuffs and Serges: But if the care of our Anceſtors was ſuch, in a leſs quantity, to preſerve our reputation abroad, the ſame reaſon is certainly ſtrengthened by its increaſe: But for farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, I will here inſert a particular Character that I ſaw of its reputation from <hi>Smyrna,</hi> which was, That the <hi>Levant</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had better buy up the raskally Pinion-Cloth, and ſet it on Fire, than ſend it thither.</p>
            <p>By another publick Declaration, from the ſame place, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that ſeveral Perſons that bought quantities of it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by it. One <hi>Cariboyle,</hi> an <hi>Armenian,</hi> turned <hi>Turk,</hi> to have the benefit of the Laws of <hi>Turky,</hi> againſt an <hi>Engliſh Merchant</hi> that ſold him a quantity of it, and recovered one hundred and eighty Dollars.
<note n="*" place="margin">Albyn's Caſe.</note> —</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40262:11"/>
            <p>Its reputation abroad, when experienc'd, farther appears by its ſhifting at home, and appearing at Market, like <hi>Proteus,</hi> in changeable Shapes of all the Letters of the Alphabet.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>homo trium nominum,</hi> was a character of eminence of old, what muſt four and twenty make?—<hi>homo trium literarum</hi> to the publick.</p>
            <p>And that this Cloth may be well ſuited with Buttons, I can't but recommend <hi>Bengall</hi>-Silk, (the kindneſs of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, in return of our Bullion) being near of a quality for ſervice. The unhappy effects of which ſufficiently appear at this time, when you ſhall not ſee one Man in five that hath any Silk upon a Button, a great check to the Woollen-Manufacture.</p>
            <p>And I doubt not but Pinion-Cloth hath wrought the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects abroad, put People, in many places, upon ſetting up ſome Fabrick of their own.</p>
            <p>A deceitful Commodity will ſoon bring its ſelf out of eſteem, and can never bear up againſt Experience.</p>
            <p>The advantage we got upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> in the way of Batter at the firſt, is known only by private Perſons, but the effect more publick at home, and the Cheat, paid to the Silk-man; as much deceit appearing in the opening of a Bail of Ardaſs Silk, as there could be in Pinion-Cloth, and conditional Bargains, for the moſt part, made in the Commodity.</p>
            <p>And how unhappy muſt the conſequence of this be, on both ſides, to a Publick Good, when our Cloth is the only proper Commodity for the <hi>Turks,</hi> and their Silk altogether as uſeful to us? And how uneaſie muſt Trade be carried on, when there is a miſtruſt and jealouſie on both ſides, where it can't well be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged but by a dependance upon Reputation and Honeſty?</p>
            <p>Another Argument of advantage to the Publick, ariſes from the greater conſumption of Cloth that would be occaſion'd here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. If this Cloth were mark'd, and ſold according to its merit, the Price of it thereby would be leſſened; and it would come into many hands that can't now reach the Price of Cloth, and be avoided by others, that are now deceived by it, and hindred from good Fleece-Wool Cloth that they expected; and hereby the Price of Good Cloth would be more advanc'd than the other leſſened, conſidering the quantity. And further, if this Cloth was mark'd, and well known amongſt our ſelves, it would be ſure to be ſent abroad on its proper Errand. Should a <hi>Merchant</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40262:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſend a quantity of Bays to <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> his Intellect in Trade would be call'd in queſtion in ſo cold a Climate; and the ſame, ſhould a well-made Piece of Drab-Cloth, be ſent into <hi>Spain.</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Pinion looſe Cloth may be much properer in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> where it is made into looſe Garments, that are not put to ſtreſs, than in <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> where no Cloth can be too good to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in ſo frigid a Climate: And I may confidently affirm, that the decay and loſs of that Trade is very much owing to Pinion bad Cloth; to retrieve which <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Trade, there can be no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perer undertaking, in purſuance of a Publick Good: But this will be crying ſtinking Fiſh abroad. The Golden Rule, we ſay, is to do as we would be done by. Should a Gentleman ſend his Servant into the Market to buy a Lamprey (a Fiſh of value) and he ſhould be put upon with a Conger-Eel, and the Cheat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the Maſter's Palate, would it not ſit uneaſie in his Stomach? or ſhould <hi>Compechia</hi> or <hi>Silveſter</hi> be ſold for <hi>Cechinele,</hi> being much alike, it would be a Cheat to the Buyer, altho' both of them will make a grain Colour, and the Price being propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to the merit of each, it can be no hindrance to either: And why is the <hi>Tower</hi> mark put upon Plate? Our reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, in this particular, is of greater value to the Intereſt of the Nation, than at home, conteſting there with other Nations. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, how many Imprecations hath been powered out upon us, by this occaſion to the firſt, ſecond, and third Generation, and the name of God blaſphemed amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> thro' us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? We read of the Primitive Chriſtians in the Skins of wild Beaſts, but lo! here are wild Beaſts in the Skins of Chriſtians, devouring <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Armenians:</hi> And how reflecting for an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menian</hi> to turn <hi>Turk,</hi> and recover in this manner of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> it hath, I think, loudly enough proclaim'd its quality, without a Cryer, and prov'd ſo ſnappiſh a Cur in our Ware houſes abroad, that it is not only our generous Intereſt, but neceſſity, to ſhew its Muzel, and <hi>Salomon</hi> decides the point, who tells us, <hi>That Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs exalts a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>It is no leſs the ſubject of admiration than pity, and indeed notorious in fact, that the Woollen-Manufacture, which is (and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40262:12"/>hath always been eſteem'd) the Glory of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, ſhould be thus imbas'd, and become the free ſubject of each Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers private Intereſt.</p>
            <p>And whereas, thirty years laſt paſt, it was the ſtudy and great care, both of <hi>Merchant</hi> and <hi>Clothier,</hi> that the goodneſs of the Commodity ſhould be preſerved according to its Worthineſs: Within this twenty years laſt paſt, the current of Trade hath run as violent in the contrary Channel; and that Clothier found the moſt incouragement in the <hi>Merchants</hi> way, that made it the moſt ſlight and deceitful; it is become almoſt a Cheat in its ſelf, that it may thereby be made the ſubject of a greater, in its exceſſive ſtraining of it; in both which particulars, we are now arrived to ſuch perfection, that it's but reaſonable to think, that this is the laſt parcel of Cloth we intend to ſell the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhame indeed, that ſuch Cloth ſhould be ſeen abroad, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the name of <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſeen Cloth that was ſent to <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> not many years ſince, that I am well aſſur'd, that a judicious Woollen Draper would not give two ſhillings a yard for it, who knew its ſervice. This now being become ſo general a Diſtemper, and experienced in all our Markets abroad, the ſole deſign of this Article of our Bill, is firſt to redreſs the bad making of our Cloth at home, and then to teſtifie the ſame abroad by theſe ſignal Letters of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, according to the ancient practice of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, who commanded the ſame, by the Letter <hi>E</hi> Crown'd.</p>
            <p>And altho', there is nothing propos'd in this Bill for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, I hope it will be added by better judgment; the only offer I can make is the holding <hi>Merchants</hi> Cloth to a weight, and preventing the exceſſive ſtraining of it.</p>
            <p>The reputation of any Commodity is no ſmall advantage to the ſale of it, whilſt we are in emulation abroad with other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: And were our care in improving the Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture anſwerable to the benign favour of Providence, in afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us means and incouragements, we muſt certainly out ſhine the whole World in this excellent Commodity. But the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Woollen-Manufacture, to bring it to its due perfection, requires as great care, experience, and judgment, as any Commodity in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; and to have it undertaken by all ſorts, that have not been duly and regularly brought up to it, is a great diſcouragement to the Trade it ſelf, and thoſe that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40262:12"/>are induſtrious in it, and brings a great diſ-reputation upon the Commodity it ſelf. Theſe abuſes being regulated, we ſhould build upon a ſure foundation, and the very <hi>Turks</hi> may become ſharers in our late deliverance.</p>
            <p>And this brings me to the laſt part of our Bill, that all long Cloth ſhall be made of one limited length.</p>
            <p>It appears in former Statutes
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quarto Jacobi cap.</hi> 2.</note>, that it was as great a Penalty for making Cloth too long as too ſhort.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, We find it a great eaſe in Trade, by a cuſtomary Sale of our <hi>Merchants</hi> Cloth, at ſo much the whole Cloth, it prevents many inconveniencies in the difficulty of meaſure, and there can be no preſervation of this, but by the exacteſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that we can arrive to in our lengths. And ſhould we once break bounds in this particular, there would be no ſtop, the <hi>Merchants</hi> deſire would grow larger than our Timber to make Stocks to mill the Cloth, and we ſhould only hereby endeavour to ſupplant each other in Trade, by giving privately a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allowance herein.</p>
            <p>And in the next place, many parts of the wages belonging to the Trade, having a long time been ſettled at ſo much by the Cloth, it will come hard upon the laborious part of the Trade; and it would likewiſe be too heavy a burthen to our Pack-Horſes, in ſo long a Journey. And I think this grievance wants little more ground for Reformation, having been already tedious: And thus much for what particularly relates to our Bill.</p>
            <p>Several Objections ariſe againſt our Bill, but the moſt plauſible, That it will ruine all the little Clothiers, if they are forc'd to come up to ſell ſmall quantities of Cloth.</p>
            <p>The making of a leſs quantity of Cloth than a Bail, which is five Cloths, and in value thirty five or forty Pounds in the <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> way, is an Obſtruction to the Sale. The Factorage of theſe is five and twenty Shillings: This being ſaved, it will very well bear the charge of the Journey. And Experience ſhews us, that few little Clothiers, that now make any Cloth, but do come up with their Cloth, altho' they ſave nothing by their Journey; and there could not be one Journey in two ſaved, as it's now managed.</p>
            <p>The trial of advantage or loſs, to little Clothiers, in this caſe, muſt chiefly depend, between the kindneſs of the <hi>Merchant,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40262:13"/>the kindneſs of the Factor. If a <hi>Merchant</hi> buy five Cloths of a little Clothier, and in kindneſs to him, order him to make five more as good, and ſend them up to him, and draw a Bill upon him for the Money; the kindneſs of the <hi>Merchant</hi> in going to <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> and ordering the Hall-Keeper to ſend them in to him, will as well ſave a Clothier a Journey as the Factor; and if half the Factorage be allowed on the Price to the <hi>Merchant,</hi> it will be felt.</p>
            <p>And if Trade was in the old Channel, that Cloth was ſold for ready Money, the little Clothier need not fear the Sale of his Cloth in a time of demand for Cloth; if he came up in a dull time, a little abatement would always find ready Money; and if he had his Money, and made but the ſame quantity of Cloth again, the Money earned by his Family out of the Cloth would be conſiderable. And the Factor can do no more to ſell Cloth in a dull time, than the Clothier himſelf. But, quoth the Factor, we then lend the Clothier Money: This, by the rule <hi>Solomon,</hi> at the firſt ſtroke, inverts the order, and puts the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the Maſter's place, who tells us, That the <hi>Borrower</hi> is Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the <hi>Lender;</hi> and from whence this Money came, I ſhall not inquire: This ſmelt a little of the Cask to the Committee. This kindneſs is like a Bucket of Water to a dry Pump, only to ſet a ſtream going, which will ſoon bring the poor Clothier in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Diabetis.</hi> The Money will be ſure to be wanting at ſuch a time that his Price muſt be beaten down, to procure it, or the Factor become <hi>Merchant,</hi> which is worſe. What <hi>Laocoon</hi> obſerv'd of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> may be very ſerviceable to us in an offer'd kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from a Factor, <hi>Timeo Danaos &amp; dona ferentes:</hi> Some pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate deſign being at the end of it; and I wholly ſubmit herein to the Experience that theſe Clothiers have found.</p>
            <p>Many miſerable Inſtances have appear'd of late years at the death of thoſe Clothiers that are in this way of Trade, which would be too tedious to relate; as in the Caſe of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Gardmer,</hi> in the County of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> the one making eight or ten Cloths a Week, and the other twelve or fourteen, both dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this flouriſhing Trade; the one left not above one hundred Pounds to his own Relation, and the other never paid his own juſt Debts in the Country.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40262:13"/>
            <p>Another tumultuous Clamour ariſes againſt our Bill, from the Pinion Intereſt, purſuing the exact meaſures of <hi>Demetrim,</hi> the Silver-ſmith, foot by foot. <hi>Sir,</hi> ye know by this Craft we have our Wealth; our Craft is in danger of being ſet at naught; and all the Intereſt crieth out for two hours, <hi>Great is</hi> Diana <hi>of the</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians: In like manner, when Pinion-Cloth was like to be mark'd in good earneſt.</p>
            <p>This narrow-ſpirited Intereſt, like a drowning Man, catcheth at every ſprig to preſerve it ſelf. <hi>Sir,</hi> Its impoſſible to make courſe Cloth to hold ſix Quarters: This exactneſs will ruine our Trades that make courſe Cloth. If this Bill paſs, I muſt turn off all my Weavers; and in this great tumult and concourſe, mercenary Meſſengers were diſpatch'd with all Expedition to all Quarters, with blanck Papers to get Subſcriptions to the Factors Petition to the Parliament; in which hot Enterprize, ſome of the Undertakers (doubtleſs hoping their Wages would riſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Subſcriptions) perſwaded many of the ignorant Work People, it was to ſuppreſs the <hi>Blackwell-Hall</hi> Factors, and thereby prevail'd.</p>
            <p>Learned <hi>Tully,</hi> who was a true Patriot of his Country, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh'd, that every Man's Eſtate might be proportion'd to his good to the Publick. Should <hi>Tully</hi>'s wiſh prevail, it would make a ſtrange Metamorphoſis in our days.</p>
            <p>I think now I can't be thought altogether impertinent in an indifferent Eſſay (keeping within the compaſs of my promiſe) whil'ſt we are under the ſenſible preſſures of our own neglect and folly.</p>
            <p>Nothing hath more impoveriſh'd this Nation, than the loſs of our Wool into <hi>France,</hi> and the extraordinary growth of ſo many Wool broggers in the City of <hi>London, Southwark,</hi> and adjacent places. I think 'em therefore fit to be treated upon together, from their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: The lovs of our Wool being an immediate loſs to our ſelves, and advance to <hi>France;</hi> the quantity may be better made out by other hands, but upon all accounts very conſiderable; the value of our loſs in ordinary Wool, is above the worth of the Wool in the Manufacture; in Worſted Wool, made into Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, fine Stuffs, Druggets, and the like, four or five times the value of the Wool; the meeting us abroad at Markets with our own Growth, the incouraging their own Wool, by a mixture of ours,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40262:14"/>and working ſo much cheaper in <hi>France,</hi> had need of a better Arithmetician for the ſumming it up.</p>
            <p>The Wool brogger, in being inſtrumental to the imbaſing the Woollen Manufacture, and loſing its reputation abroad; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (if many Men are not miſtaken) in forwarding the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <p>The beginning of which growing miſchief, (evidently in the Wool brogger, and, I think, impliedly in the other) I compute from the 20th of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, where I find a repeal of the good Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Anno quinto, cap.</hi> 7. that had continued in force Seventy years: The effect of which, I think, may be deſcribed in the pathetical Complaint of the Poet in a like caſe.
<q>
                  <l>Fugêre pudor, verum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fideſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</l>
                  <l>In quorum ſubiêre locum fraudeſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> doli<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſidiae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; vis, &amp; amor ſceleratus habendi.</l> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q> The condition of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation (by the Preamble of the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Anno quinto, cap.</hi> 6.) ſeems to run parallel with our preſent times, where it is thus expreſs'd, <hi>That many Clothiers, for lack of Knowledge and Experience, and ſome of extream Covetouſneſs, do daily more and more ſtudy rather to make many, than to make good Cloths, having more reſpect to their private Commodity and Gain, than the advancement of Truth, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Commodity, in eſtimation according to the worthineſs of it, have, and do daily, inſtead of Truth, practiſe Falſhood; and inſtead of ſubſtantial making of Cloth, do practiſe ſlight and ſlender making of Cloth, by mingling Fell Wool and Lambs-Wool,</hi> &amp;c. No ſuch thing as Pinions in thoſe days.</p>
            <p>After a due care taken in that Statute to preſerve the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Woollen-Manufacture, by the beſt means that could be then thought of, conſulting all Artificers in the Trade, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Statute I now mention, where all Perſons were ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibited from buying any Wool, upon a double Forfeiture of the value of the ſaid Wool, unleſs they ſpun it into a Yarn, or made it into ſome ſort of Manufacture; and no Clothier to have any aſſiſtance in buying of Wool, but by Servants, abiding in his Manſion-Houſe, which Statute was made in thoſe days with a great deal of debate and conſideration, as appears by a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40262:14"/>Clauſe in the ſaid Statute, which is almoſt ſingular, that the King, by his Proclamation, ſhould Diſſolve the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. After five Years Experience, there was an Appeal made to the Parliament, by the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> where dwelt a conſiderable number of poor Traders, that could not buy Horſes to fetch in their Wool, but had always been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to buy ſmall parcels of the Wool-Drivers, and carry it home upon their heads; and they deſir'd the ſame liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which, upon particular conſideration, I find, was obtained, but the Statute more ſtrictly confirm'd in the general; and thoſe Wool-drivers of <hi>Hallifax</hi> were ſtrictly limitted to that Town, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a double forfeiture of their Wool; as appears by the Statute of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary; Secundo &amp; tertio Phil. &amp; Mariae, cap.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Which is plain demonſtration, that they found a benefit to the Publick, by that Statute which afterwards continued in force all the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and to the twentieth of King <hi>James,</hi> and then Repealed. The ſtrictneſs of which Statute, and extraordinary Penalty of Forfeiture of double the value of the ſaid Wool, and remarkable caution, that the Clothier ſhould have no aſſiſtance in buying of Wool, but by his own immediate Servants, ſeems to provide againſt this double miſchief: Firſt the imbaſing of our Cloth; Wool being a Commodity that will ſhelter more deceit than the warieſt Buyer can diſcover, as was never better known than at this day.</p>
            <p>In the next place, it ſeems to fence againſt the Exportation of our Wool.</p>
            <p>It's very evident, that had we no Recetters, we could not be liable to theſe <hi>French</hi> Thieves; no <hi>French</hi> Man could come and buy Wool openly.</p>
            <p>The buying of Wool being ſtrictly confin'd to the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, it's unlikely, upon ſeveral conſiderations, that they ſhould be concerned in this practice; nay, I think, almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable: Firſt, the remoteneſs of their living from the places that are proper for this purpoſe, as <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and the like, no Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing parts being within fifty Miles of it, and thereby uncapable of waiting for ſeaſonable times, for the delivery of it to <hi>French</hi> Shalops.</p>
            <p>In the next place, This Wool muſt be paid for by <hi>French</hi> Bills, or by ſome <hi>French</hi> Man living in <hi>London:</hi> This way is very difficult to be found out, and adjuſted by one that is a Stranger a <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40262:15"/>and the practice it ſelf is directly contrary to the Intereſt of their own Trades: It is not time ill ſpent, when we are ſenſing againſt an Enemy, to conſider which way we are like leaſt to be attack'd.</p>
            <p>How fair now doth all this come to hand with theſe Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broggers, living in <hi>London,</hi> and adjacent places? They buy up all the Wool that grows fair for the practice, as <hi>Rumney-Marſh, &amp;c.</hi> Afterwards they pack it up, and leave it at the Breeders Houſes, until conveniencies of ſending for it: This being ready pack'd up, how eaſie is it to let ſome part be brought to <hi>London,</hi> and the other to a <hi>French</hi> Shalop: The buying part is in their own way, and can give no miſtruſt; the bringing part for <hi>London,</hi> a ſhelter to the other for <hi>France.</hi> Communication with <hi>French</hi>-Men at <hi>London,</hi> to adjuſt opportunities of meeting at an exact time, and any correſpondence in <hi>France,</hi> by Letters of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce without notice, <hi>French</hi> Bills which uſually come over, at double uſance, as well to be managed by them in point of time, as is poſſible: And that they have been concerned in this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, I think, is evident by the appearance of a double quantity of Wool in their hands. At the beginning of our <hi>French</hi> Wars Wool was not cheaper to incourage it in the Buying part: The dulneſs of Trade gave opportunities of truſting greater quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to their old Traders; and nothing, I think, but a back door ſtop'd could occaſion it.</p>
            <p>Here are a conſiderable Party of Men that flouriſh like <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Lilies, that neither toyl nor ſpin, that only get a Profit out of the Wool, and no way incourage the Woollen-Manufacture; but on the contrary, a Pack of Wool carried forty Miles backwards and forwards, will not make the more Cloth at the Journies end, I wiſh I could ſay it would not make leſs. No Farmer that hath long Wool, that is fit for Combing, and ſhort Wool that is fit for Clothing, but may eaſily have it divided, either by Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their or Comber. And in carrying on any conſiderable Trade in the Nation, it ſeems a fair queſtion to know, What good to the Publick?</p>
            <p>By an Artificer at Mouſe-Traps, we have a ſecurity to our Cheeſe and Bacon: By an Ingineer at Pigs-Rings, a check to the miſchievous nature of the Swine: By an Artiſt at Save-alls, a thriſty help to make the moſt of the Candle: The Scavenger and Goldfinder are uſeful in their proper Seaſons; but <hi>Cui bono,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40262:15"/>theſe Men? their uſefulneſs to the Publick is much like that of the Hedge-Hog; they wrap themſelves up in warm Wool, and prick the Fingers of all their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Traders.</p>
            <p>The true ſpring of all ſubſtantial Commerce, ought to ariſe from a real benefit that accrues thereby to the Publick, either immediately to our ſelves, or which is ſerviceable to other Parts, and thereby brings home an advantage, and the undoubted or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the great Creator of the Univerſe, who did nothing in vain.</p>
            <p>The private ingroſſing of Commodities, to no other end than to advance the Price, is only a Private Intereſt preying upon the Publick; and I think the ſame reaſon to prevent Ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Materials in Trade, as it is in the concern of Life; this being but one degree a remoter cauſe. To inſtance at preſent in <hi>Cochinele</hi> and <hi>Indigo,</hi> both which are very material Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities in the preſent courſe of the Woollen-Manufacture, and both theſe Commodities lately Ingroſſed, and thereby the Prizes very much Inhanc'd. The advantage of this is only to the Ingroſſers.</p>
            <p>A pound of <hi>Cochinele</hi> will make no better a colour coming out of their hands, after advanc'd ten or fifteen Shillings, than when they took it in: This extraordinary profit muſt be made good by the Publick; and indeed this Year it hath been an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary check to fine Cloth.</p>
            <p>Nay, to come nearer, great part of this private Profit hath been made good by the Officers of our Army, that fight for our ſecurity, and the luſtre of the Colour, weakened by their private Profit. Were the practice of Ingroſſing Foreign Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities nearly conſidered, it will appear to be an advantage to Foreign Parts, and a weakning of our ſelves: When a Foreign Commodity, by this means, is advanc'd here, that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, the Price is advanc'd abroad, and only an incouragement to a droniſh Intereſt at home, that hereby preys upon the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and a Stock that lieth lurking for this purpoſe, kept out of Trade, where it might do good; which is a Grievance upon the Woollen-Manufacture, which, I hope, will be Redreſs'd.</p>
            <p>The Experience of the Growth of <hi>France</hi> will, I hope, quicken our Care in the reviving of the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth; which for its worth to the publick Good, deſerveth to be wrote in Letters of Gold; and that the ſeverity of the Statute againſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40262:16"/>of Wool will be turned into the full Reward of the value of the Wool to the Seizer or Diſcoverer, with the leaſt trouble that can be contrived: And that any Perſon or Perſons that ſhall be found aiding or aſſiſting in the Deſign of Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Wool, ſhall be liable to ſo many Years Impriſonment: The one (is evident) hath not anſwered its end in a true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and on the other hand, nothing like a clear Reward to quicken Diligence.</p>
            <p>And for a Proof of the Repeal of the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, could the Gentlemen in <hi>Suſſex</hi> truly inform themſelves of the Price of their Wool in the flouriſhing time of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and compare it with twenty years laſt paſt, I dare ſay they would be for having this Statute reviv'd, notwithſtanding their fairneſs to Exportation: And to argue that if theſe Wool-Broggers did not buy their Wool, it would remain upon their Hands unſold, is but ſhort-ſighted Reaſoning. If a Clothier in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> could buy Wool a Farthing in a Pound cheaper in <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi> than his own County, his love to his County would not ſway that Intereſt, if he had the free command of his own Stock. And to deſire ſuch Aſſiſtance as this in a dull time of Trade (which hath always its Ebbings and Flowings) is no other than the deſire of a draught of cold Drink in a High Fever, which will return with double Vigour the next Fit; and People in ſuch a heat ought to have ſome care took of them.</p>
            <p>And no need of an Argument to prove the Sway of private Intereſt, when it ſhall openly appear to procure a free Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Wool, and be willing freely to part with ſo valuable a Jewel; whoſe Intellect muſt be greatly informed, did they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the low condition of the Nation, when our Wool was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried abroad to be Manufactured, before the days of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, when the Government was chiefly ſupported by a Duty paid out of our Wool Exported; and when fourteen pound of Wool was ſold here for eighteen-Pence
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viceſimo quinto Hen.</hi> 8. ca. 13.</note>; when the Subjects of <hi>Edward</hi> I. were ſo much grieved at the Toll they payed out of their Wool, of Forty Shillings for every Sack
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viceſimo quinto Edw</hi> 1. ca. 7.</note>; and when there was a Subſidy granted to <hi>Edward</hi> III. of the ninth Fleece, the ninth Lamb, and the ninth Sheaf, to carry on a War in <hi>France</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Decimo quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Edw.</hi> 3. ca. 20.</note>. In thoſe days, when our Wool was carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to be Manufactured, and Trade had brought home no better ways of raiſing of Money. And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40262:16"/>the extraordinary care of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third to encourage the Manufacturing of it here
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Decimo quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Edw.</hi> 3. ca. 5.</note>, by allowing Cloth-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of a ſtrange Land more Priviledge than his own Subjects: The encreaſe of which, hath plainly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd the Riches of this Nation, a Jewel of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Value than rightly underſtood, according to the Judgment of Famous <hi>Coke,</hi> who computes that Nine Parts in Ten of our exported Commodities do come from the Sheeps Back. The Value of Wool indeed is not enough underſtood amongſt us, or at leaſt too little conſidered; a Commodity capable of being converted to almoſt any Uſe, and adapted to the Humour and Uſefulneſs of hot and cold Climates; and ſtill carrying a true Merit with it, not only the Bread of the Nation, but, like <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Locks, in it conſiſts our Strength and Security; our Foreign Trade depending upon the Woollen-Manufacture, and our Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping our Bulwarks; and if People are our Riches, and Forrage as well the Support of a War, as the Soldiers that fight the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, both ought jointly to be conſidered: And that we want People in this Nation, I think admits no queſtion. I will paſs by the Conſideration of the immediate Advantage to our ſelves in the employment of the laborious part of the Nation, and thereby affecting the Value of the other Produce of the Ground, and the Uſefulneſs and Beauty to our ſelves, in ſo good and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teel a Clothing, and only take notice of its kind Effects that it brings us from abroad.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, (that Right may take place) from <hi>Turky,</hi> by the Honourable <hi>Levant</hi> Company, abundance of Raw-Silk, Grograms, Yarn, Cotton-Wool; all which are uſeful Commodities, and employ numerous hands here. From <hi>Hamburgh, Germany,</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> all ſorts of Linens ſuitable to all Occaſions. From <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> our Bullion, Spaniſh-Wool, Corn, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinele. From <hi>Ruſſia, Dantzick,</hi> and the Eaſt Country, Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſhes, Flax, Hemp, uſeful to our Shipping, all ſubſtantial and needful Commodities; by which the Merchants fetch the Money from the Nobility and Gentry, in a ſubſtantial Circulation of Affairs; not Humm-Humms, and Mull-Mulls, Callicoes and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for borrowed Bullion. 'Twas never well with this Nation ſince we have endeavoured ſo much to make a ſhew without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and built Caſtles in the Air for Stock-jobbings. And if ſo many Advantages to the Nation, and ſo excellent a crop of Fruit
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40262:17"/>from this fair Tree, how reflecting is the neglect of it, when the Suckers and uſeleſs Scyons over-top the true Branches, and a ſeeming Conteſt between the Sons of the Bond-woman and the Free?</p>
            <p>Nor is it inconſiderable how far the Artificers in the Woollen-Manufacture do otherwiſe contribute to the Support of the Government.</p>
            <p>Theſe are thoſe good Subjects that chiefly delight in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Indian Weed, meaſuring time by the Pipe; and will ſooner ſuffer a Famine in the Cupboard than the Box; which in a plenty time of Trade is too good a Shooe-horn to the Liquid Exciſe; many of theſe chuſing rather to wear their Hands by hard Labour than part with their Liquor: An Advantage as well to the Crown as the Farmer.</p>
            <p>And as our Woollen-Manufacture (ariſing out of the Country) doth yield theſe good Advantages, and bring us home theſe neceſſary Commodities; and likewiſe the chief Dependance of our Trade at home, is upon the Conſumption of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities amongſt our ſelves, (little Goods brought to <hi>England</hi> that is carried to other Dominions, and an Advantage thereby, as in <hi>Holland.</hi> I wiſh I could ſay we had all our own at the firſt Hand: And if I had enough of Father <hi>Latimer</hi>'s Gravity to make a Wiſh, it ſhould be confin'd to the narrow compaſs of a Nutmeg, to rub my Toaſt that was brought to <hi>England</hi> at the firſt Hand.) This muſt likewiſe receive its Life, and ebb and flow, according to the Revenue of our Land: The Streams can't riſe higher than the Fountain: As our Wool encreaſes, our Trade; as our Trade encreaſes, our People. And what the witty <hi>Cowley</hi> propoſeth in his Agriculture, To have one Colledge in each U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity appropriated to the encouragement of Husbandry, hath much reaſon in it: And had he added the Shepherds Crook to his Plough in the Field Arable, it had certainly been the proper Arms of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Value of the whole Nation at this time, I dare ſay, is one fifth part loſt for want of Skill to manure, and Money to Stock it. Ill Husbandry is the Off-ſpring of Poverty. To find out the true cauſe of this, the Gentleman muſt leave the City, and come to his ancient Manſion-Houſe in the Country; where he will find but Five hundred Sheep upon a Farm, that if manured to the heighth would keep Seven.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40262:17"/>
            <p>In ſhort, The City hath ſo drained the Country, that there is not Money enough left to make the moſt of Eſtates. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we have had a better Advantage than our Fore-Fathers in the Return of our Money by Bills of Exchange, (a neat and ſecure way of doing of Buſineſs,) it were better for the Country if they run the ſame Hazard that they did. This Practice hath brought the Wallet too much upon one ſide; the City is cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome by its bigneſs, and the Country ſtarved.</p>
            <p>But I return to the Woollen-Manufacture: out of which there is, upon modeſt Computation, One hundred thouſand Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> carried away by thoſe Perſons that no way encourage it; who live ſplendidly, and neither plough nor ſow, which poſſibly may be their proper part. How valuable this is to a publick Good to have ſuch a dead Weight hanged upon the Maſter-wheel of our Trade, when we are in Competition with other Nations, is beyond my Arithmetick, and doubles, in my Thoughts, as the price of a Horſe at a Penny a Nail. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever unneceſſary Charge we ſuffer to clog this Commodity, is plainly a hindrance to the publick Good: And if that Duty that is now paid out of our Cloth Exported was doubled to the Crown ſome way or other upon Importation, it might be our Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. This is but ſhooing our Horſe with Lead (the Simile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at hand) that is to run for our Plate.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot paſs by the Glory of the Aulnage Court without a little Obſervation, its large Revenue ariſing out of the Woollen-Manufacture. This Court having made fairer Footſteps to Arbitrary Power in the late times, than the High-Commiſſion-Court could attain to. Theſe Aulnagers firſt ſeized Cloth, then laid Fines, heard their own Cauſes, and determined; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they impos'd was effectual Execution before you had your Goods: nay, their under Officers made their own Fees: Every Jackdaw and Rooke will ſteal a Lock from the poor Sheeps Back to make his Neſt eaſie.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company with their Stock, reſolv'd to have one Cloth go for two, as Aulnagers, willing enough to have two Cloths, Forrels and all, at the old Price of one, as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40262:18"/>
               <hi>Caninus appetitu,</hi> needs a Phyſician. Theſe prevail'd two Years, and reſolv'd to carry all before them, (being ſtill fluſh'd with Succeſs at the Exchequer-Bar;) they ſeiz'd Forty long Cloths of one Man's that would not comply with their Arbitrary Proceedings, of the value of Four hundred Pounds, and kept them almoſt a Year, the matter in diſpute being only Ten Shillings; and one Cloth might have been Pledge enough, had they not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhewn their Power and Arbitrary Greatneſs; the beſt Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in Town at this time for Woollen Goods.</p>
            <p>All at this Court went current on their ſides, being Judge and Jury both: And where they ſaid the Hares Ears muſt go for Horns, as in the Creation it was, ſo Hats, Stockings, Stuffs, Serges; nay, in our muliſh Commodities, the Wool muſt bear the Sway, and all ſummoned to Court, and accordingly appear'd. They had ſcarce paſt by the Kitching-Maids Mopps being made of Wool, had not the ſharpneſs of <hi>Joan</hi>'s Temper ſcal'd 'em, and a liquid Entertainment at the Summons, and indeed built upon valuable Conſideration. Wages without Work is the way to make Men arbitrary and imperious. Could the Fleece of the Devil be manufactured, when he was to appear upon the Earth; or <hi>Mahomet</hi> in the likeneſs of a Ram, you may have a Seal at this Office,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecce iterum Criſpinus &amp; eſt mihi ſaepe vocandus Ad partes.</hi> Juv.</note> to ſhew it to be a current Commodity, and one better or other in Four and twenty, to make a Cloth-mark, was there any thing to be got by it. But this Subject hath been well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and I hope we are near a Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing I humbly offer (having, I doubt, been too tedious already) being of great concern to the Publick, and a check to the Woollen Manufacture, was the breaking the Company of Merchant-Adventurers.</p>
            <p>It evidently appear'd to the Obſervation of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate makers of Cloth, that had a dependance upon the <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> Trade, that the breaking of that Company in former days, was a very deftructive Act to the Clothing Trade; and from that very time Reputation in the Cloth Trade began to decline; and the Subſtantial Credit that had been many Years main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40262:18"/>in a regular fair Trade, ſhipping off Cloth conſtantly twice or three times a Year was ſoon interlop'd away.</p>
            <p>This was introduc'd by a great pretence of the Dog in the Manger, and colour of Reformation and Amendment of Trade (<hi>A la mode</hi> at that time) which ſoon appear'd in its true Effects like the reſt; and the ſame Cloth that was ſold at Twelve Pounds <hi>per</hi> Cloth, was ſoon brought down to Ten; and ſince by degrees, to Nine, matter of Fact and to be proved.</p>
            <p>The Clothiers that were prevail'd upon (by the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers) to Petition for it, were gratified in their deſire; exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like the Frogs, who petitioned to <hi>Jupiter</hi> for a new King, making a great complaint of the dulneſs of the Beam that he firſt ſent them: and to ſatisfie their deſire in the contrary, he ſent them the Stork. The Truth of this Simile is very well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred at this day, by the extraordinary Abatements, cheat in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, only the middle of the Cloth paid for by ſome, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſharp'd out of the Clothier to maintain the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loper <hi>Kitchin,</hi> as was reckoned in the heighth of thoſe times. But theſe Merchants were in great meaſure ſupplanted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in a ſhort time, by another ſort of Merchants that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſprung up, that are one degree worſe than the Stork. And could not the Devil appear in any Shape, and only known, they ſay, by his Cloven Foot, one could never believe to have met a Factor in this Station; and yet too true to make a Jeſt. Here will be large Thongs cut out of the publick Hide! to encourage his Commiſſions from abroad, and lumping Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths of Cloth ſent out; and let the King beware of his Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms when Factors ſell Nutmegs.</p>
            <p>One would have thought it impoſſible for two ſuch oppoſite Intereſts to be undertaken by the ſame Hand, (but this difficult point meeting with ſo great Integrity and vaſt Parts, the <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian</hi> Oracle, by the ſecret whiſpers of his Lips,) is kept as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right as Juſtice it ſelf. But it evidently appears, that the Man is at great pains to do it, for he is forc'd to chew all his Words before he delivers them out, that one Intereſt may be kept private from the other; if not, there would be ſuch
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40262:19"/>interferings, that it would be impoſſible to be managed: Half Merchant, half Factor, ſounds a little old. Let with great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, the one part in this Caſe may be ſerviceable to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The firſt Letter being diſpatch'd to the Correſpondent abroad, to acquaint him (for his Encouragement) how good a Pennyworth of Cloth he can now ſend him, ſomething cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the laſt. The next Letter falls on courſe to the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier: <hi>Sir, Ireceived your Cloths, and am ſorry I can give you no better Encouragement: Here are ſuch vaſt quantities of Cloth ſent from other Parts, and they daily under-ſell us; ſo that unleſs I comply a little, I muſt be forc'd to ſtand ſtill, and light the Candle.</hi> —</p>
            <p>It's almoſt incredible what thirty or forty Years neglect in Trade may produce, and what monſtrous Shapes by long uſe may grow familiar, and little notice took: And the Myſteries of Trade are now thought ſo deep and abſtruſe, like the Rabbins Greek. <hi>Non poteſt leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> We want ſome of the Race of publick-ſpirited <hi>Tully<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> temporit! Oh mores!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only knowledge of Interloping, that appears to my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, (being wholly a Stranger abroad) is only this, That ſome Foreigners, either Merchants or Shop-keepers, living with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limits of the ancient Charter of the <hi>Hamburgh</hi> Company, ſhall have the free liberty of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Market for what Cloth they pleaſe; as likewiſe for the Sale of any of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Goods, at ſo much <hi>per Cent.</hi> as they can make their Bargain with ſome Packer or Factor. This belief of mine is grounded upon this plain appearance, That theſe are the Men that buy the Cloth of us for thoſe Parts; and not above two or three <hi>Hamburgh</hi> Merchants that now buy any Cloth: What room there is left at this rate for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant, is to me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible; I think, in the ſame condition as the ancient Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Trade in the Country; <hi>Et ſolamen miſeris ſocios habuiſſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris,</hi> if I may be ſo familiar with the Expreſſion: But, I think, both of the practices equally hurtful to the Publick: By this means the ſupport of the Credit of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> is, in great meaſure fallen into the Power of thoſe Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Merchants; for as they beat down the Price by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40262:19"/>here, upon the Clothier, and have no ſtrict regard to the true merit and excellency of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth. It hereby fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that our Cloth is much imbas'd, which is the beſt means to preferr the Cloth of their own Nation, and ſteal the Trade from us.</p>
            <p>The Clothiers care in good making of Cloth in former days, was evidently preſerved by the good judgment of the <hi>Hamburgh</hi> Merchants; and thereby we kept the Trade from the <hi>Dutch</hi> and other Nations: The loweſt Price of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth is hereby well known abroad. Nay, theſe Packers and Factors having got the Sale of Cloth wholly into their hands (and this found out by Foreign Traders) theſe are the fitteſt Men, upon ſeveral Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to be imploy'd. The Packer hath an advantage in his own Trade, and a little Commiſſion will ſerve; but theſe Packers and Factors hereby, being put upon Vying one with another who ſhall get the moſt Commiſſions; which muſt be by the beſt Penniworths. Cloth is brought one ſcotch lower than the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant himſelf could do; and, I think, a very great diſgrace to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, that our blind ſide is found out by every —</p>
            <p>The quantity of Cloth Exported by the old Company of Merchant-Adventurers, compar'd with what hath been ſent out theſe late Years in this Channel of Trade, together with the Price then and now, is both proof and motive to an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a new <hi>Hamburgh</hi> Company, and the privileges that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants enjoy at the City of <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> are too great to be ſlighted.</p>
            <p>And if any neglect (in former days) by the Company, in not ſending the Cloth, near enough for the accommodation of the Buyer (which is wiſely to be conſidered; a Piece of well-made <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth not to be ſent a begging, and the value maintain'd by a wiſe diſtance) that fault is very eaſie to be mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>Et faelix quem faciunt</hi> —</p>
            <p>A regular management of Trade, by Companies, is upon ſeveral conſiderations; The unqueſtionable Intereſt of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40262:20"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, as in keeping up its grandure at home; ſo likewiſe the Price and Value of our Cloth abroad: over-ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Market will preſently beat down the value of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity; and this can never be well gaged by private hands. It is true, That publick Companies may make themſelves of ill uſe to the Nation, if they let their private Intereſt interlope upon the Publick, and endeavour, by the delay of Shippings, to keep up the Price of Cloth too high abroad, and thereby the cheaper at home, as likewiſe, in the effects of Cloth: This will enrich a few, and impoveriſh multitudes. The true Intereſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation conſiſts in a free current of a regular Trade, managed with moderate Profit, and a true merit in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity to preſerve a good Credit abroad, with a vigilant care at home to incourage the proper effects of thoſe places that are moſt ſervicable to us in taking off our Woollen-Manufacture, by laying a good Duty upon the Commodities that herein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfere, and are brought home with our Bullion. As great a miſchief as ever, I think, happened to the Woollen-Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture, was the great quantity of <hi>Bengal</hi>-Silk brought home by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company; it viſibly made ſuch a ſtop in the Cloth-Trade, that many poor People were hereby Starved for want of Imployment.</p>
            <p>And the clearneſs of this doth ſtrangely reflect upon thoſe <hi>Turky</hi>-Merchants that ſend Money to <hi>Turky,</hi> to bring home thereby the more Silk; a falſe ſtep in that Trade, which, I think, hath been wholly occaſion'd by the loſs of our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit abroad in our Cloth, and only to help a Lame Dog over the Stile: And no wonder, at the juſt Complaint of the Farmer, when each Man's Rule in Trade hath been his own choice, and the true Intereſt of the Nation for this thirty or forty years, like <hi>Pallianurus,</hi> who ſlept at the Helm
<note n="*" place="margin">Gallico ſomno aut canino.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, I have humbly offered, (in an home-ſpun Stile) a true account of the preſent management and abuſes crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Clothing-Trade, without prejudice or deſign; wherein, if no redreſs, it will be a fair removal of the blame; being
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40262:20"/>very much incouraged hereunto, by the numerous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Acts of Parliament, made in former days, and the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal care of the Woollen-Manufacture, by our Anceſtors, in minding the higheſt Rank of our Council, by the very ſeats they ſate on: And doubt not of your honourable conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtinguiſhing care of the Country, whereby alone, the Glory of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation may be advanc'd, and we may be ſome eclipſe again to the Great Monarch <hi>Lewis le Grand;</hi> having, of late years, furniſh'd him with Wings to fly out of his own Territories, abounding in <hi>Pontacque</hi> and <hi>Nants-Brandy,</hi> and Owl'd out of the Treaſure of our Wool, Fullers-Earth, and Timber; our care in which particulars, will leſſen the Glory of <hi>France,</hi> as well in Peace as War.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
